<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The birth and burning of the image called S. Michael containing the substance of a narrative lately given into the vestry of All Saints Barkin, London / by Mr. Edmond Sherman ... at laying down his office in Easter week, 1681 ... ; together with a letter to Mr. Jonathan Saunders ... which may serve for an answer to his two late pamphlets entituled, Apparitions, &amp;c. ; introduced with two vestry orders demonstrating not so good reason for its birth as burning ; set up anno 1659/60, burnt anno 1680/81 ...</title>
            <author>Sherman, Edmund, 17th cent.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 71 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A59912</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3382</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10625</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13293085</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13293085</idno>
            <idno type="VID">98858</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A59912)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 98858)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 439:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The birth and burning of the image called S. Michael containing the substance of a narrative lately given into the vestry of All Saints Barkin, London / by Mr. Edmond Sherman ... at laying down his office in Easter week, 1681 ... ; together with a letter to Mr. Jonathan Saunders ... which may serve for an answer to his two late pamphlets entituled, Apparitions, &amp;c. ; introduced with two vestry orders demonstrating not so good reason for its birth as burning ; set up anno 1659/60, burnt anno 1680/81 ...</title>
                  <author>Sherman, Edmund, 17th cent.</author>
                  <author>Sanders, Jonathan.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and are to be sold by Richard Janeway ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Idols and images --  England --  London.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:98858:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98858:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE <hi>Birth and Burning</hi> OF THE IMAGE Called S. MICHAEL.</p>
            <p>Containing The Subſtance of a Narrative lately given into the Veſtry of <hi>All Saints Barkin London,</hi> by Mr. <hi>Edmond Sherman,</hi> late Upper Churchwarden, at laying down his Office in Eaſter Week, 1681. Fully reporting the truth of Fact relating to the Image indicted (at the Seſſions at <hi>Old Baily</hi>) by the name of <hi>S. Michael.</hi> Together with a Letter to Mr. <hi>Jonathan Saunders</hi> Lecturer, which may ſerve for an Anſwer to his two late Pamphlets entituled, <hi>Apparitions, &amp;c.</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduced with two Veſtry Orders, demonſtrating not ſo good reaſon for its Birth as Burning.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Set up Anno</hi> 1659/60. <hi>Burnt Anno</hi> 1680/81. Dedicated (Singly) to the uſe of Mr. <hi>Jonathan Saunders,</hi> Lecturer of <hi>All Saints Barkin</hi> Pariſh, without any deſign to reflect on the <hi>Clergie</hi> or <hi>Church of England.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Exod. 20.3, 4.</hi>
               </bibl> Thou ſhalt not make to thy ſelf any Graven Image, nor the likeneſs, &amp;c. Thou ſhalt not bow down to them, nor worſhip them, &amp;c.</q>
            <p>Publiſhed by a Friend of the late Churchwarden's to prevent falſe Reports.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed and are to be ſold by <hi>Richard Janeway,</hi> in Queens Head Alley in Pater Noſter Row, 1681.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:98858:2"/>
            <div type="order">
               <head>At a Veſtry held at <hi>All Saints Barkin London, April</hi> 21. 1659.</head>
               <p>
                  <list>
                     <item>Mr. Benjamin Edwards</item>
                     <item>Mr. Tho. Barret</item>
                  </list>
Churchwardens.</p>
               <p>THE Churchwardens declared the Inſufficiency of the Steeple, and Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of taking the ſame down to the ground, which was ordered to be done; and it was hereupon further ordered by this preſent Veſtry in behalf of the Pariſh, that the Churchwardens for the time being the impowe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed to take or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der for the building up of the Steeple to this Pariſh Church belonging; and to call to their aſſiſtance whom they ſhall think fit to adviſe withall; and to act and do, contract, bargain, and agree, with Workmen and others, in and upon all and every matter and thing needful and expedient for the rebuild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the ſaid Steeple.</p>
               <closer>Copia vera.
<signed>
                     <hi>Examined and compared with the Original</hi> per G. Whately <hi>Veſtry Regiſter.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
               <postscript>
                  <p>I do further certifie, That the old Steeple had not the Figures or Images of Death or Time, or of any Saint or Angel, on the inward ſide of the Steeple which ſtandeth in the Church. And I find no Order of Veſtry for the making or placing there any Image or Figure; the intent of the aboveſaid Order be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing onely to impower the then Churchwardens to take down and rebuild the Steeple. So that whatever Image or Figure was put there, was done at the pleaſure or order of the then Churchwardens, who did then cauſe this Image called <hi>S. Michael,</hi> to be made and ſet up on the Dyal between two Fretwork Figures of Death and Time, <hi>Anno 1659/60.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Certified</hi> 
                        <date>
                           <hi>April 11. 1681.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>per G. Whately <hi>Regiſter.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </postscript>
            </div>
            <div type="order">
               <head>At a Veſtry held at <hi>All Saints Barkin London, May</hi> 4. 1675.</head>
               <p>
                  <list>
                     <item>Mr. James Clement</item>
                     <item>Richard <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eck<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d Eſquire</item>
                  </list>
Churchwardens.</p>
               <p>THE preſent Churchwardens deſired the leave and conſent of this Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, to grant the Gallery at the Weſt end of the Church to ſet the Organ in; whereupon it was unanimouſly reſolved by Vote, That the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardens ſhall have liberty to alter the Gallery, and erect the Organ Frame or Caſe, and make it fit for the reception of the Organ.</p>
               <closer>Copia vera.
<signed>
                     <hi>Examined and compared with the Original</hi> per G. Whately <hi>Veſtry Regiſter.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
               <postscript>
                  <p>And I further certifie, That Mr. <hi>Clement, Anno 1675,</hi> removed the Image of the carved Saint or Angel call<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d <hi>S. Michael,</hi> from the inward ſide of the Steeple, which ſtandeth at the Weſt end of the Church, and cauſed the ſame to be placed upon or over the Commandments at the East end of the Church, without any particular Order of Veſtry for ſo doing; and that the Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures of Death and Time do ſtill remain where firſt placed.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Certified</hi> 
                        <date>
                           <hi>April 11. 1681.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>per G. Whately <hi>Regiſter.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </postscript>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:98858:2"/>
               <head>To the Reverend Doctor <hi>George Hicks</hi> Vicar, Mr. <hi>Henry Hunter</hi> and Mr. <hi>William Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Churchwardens, and to the reſt of the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of the Veſtry of the Pariſh of <hi>All Saints Barkin London.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Doctor and Gentlemen,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>BEcauſe there hath been ſuch a pother and noiſe made about a rotten, great, guilded, carved Image in our Church; and becauſe even our own Lecturer Mr. <hi>Saunders</hi> hath ſcandalized himſelf, though he aimed at me, in Printing a couple of Sham Pamphlets about it, both entituled <hi>Appariti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of an Angel, one at the Old Baily, and another at Tower Hill,</hi> which as in truth they are both but feigned Apparitions, ſo ſuitably they are falſe Relations.</p>
               <p>I ſhall therefore now give you my true Narrative of the matter of fact, to be imprinted in your Memories, and to repreſent the Royal Truth to our Succeſſors in this Pariſh.</p>
               <p>I take this opportunity to do it, upon reſignation of my Office this Thurſday in <hi>Eaſter</hi> Week, 1681; my accuſtomary ſervice of two years in the Office of Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warden being now expired.</p>
               <p>I lay down that Office at your feet with much more joy than I took it up, and wiſh you and this whole Pariſh, all happineſs and ſucceſs in the conduct of your Affairs, placed now in the Election of Mr. <hi>Henry Hunter</hi> and Mr. <hi>Will Chapman;</hi> to them and you I render this impartial Narrative, that at the Seſſions held at the <hi>Old Baily,</hi> when about three parts of the Grand Jury were of this our Ward of <hi>Tower,</hi> my ſelf the Foreman, and divers of them of our very Pariſh. Among other things there were ſome worthy Citizens that were not of the Jury, came and acquainted us, that there was offence taken at ſuch an Image in our Church, and at our Lecturer's bowing to it; and ſaid, they more particularly addreſſed to us at that time, becauſe we were ſo many of us of the ſame Pariſh, whereof our Foreman was the Churchwarden.</p>
               <p>We gave them ſuch an Anſwer as we thought neceſſary to ſatisfie them; but no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing being tendered before us upon Oath, we did nothing therein as a Grand Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. But ſoon after that Seſſions was done, I told both Dr. <hi>Hicks</hi> and Mr. <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> (and Mr. <hi>Saunders</hi> knew it alſo) that it had given offence, and that there had been a Complaint of it to the Grand Jury, and ſo it paſſed over, and I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected we ſhould hear no more of it. But it ſeems it made more noiſe, partly by our not pulling it down then, but more by Mr. <hi>Saunders</hi> his Diſcourſe in defence of the poor innocent Image, (as he was pleaſed to call it.) Inſomuch that divers ſtrangers came to our Church to ſee the Image, and our other Ceremonies, which we practiſe more than divers (I think I may ſay moſt) other Churches in <hi>England</hi> elſe.</p>
               <p>And thereupon at another Seſſions held about the end of <hi>February</hi> laſt, there was an Indictment brought and preſented (as I am informed by one Mr. <hi>Whittaker</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Oath) to the Grand Jury, that then ſerved at that Seſſions; but who was their Foreman, and who was of that Grand Jury, I know not; but ſo it was, they found the Bill, and returned it into Court <hi>Billa Vera.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>About which time I was in the Country, and heard not nor knew any thing of the Indictment, until ſome few days before the ſeventh of <hi>March,</hi> and then meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Mr. <hi>Barry</hi> laughing, asked me, Oh where have you been? you have been Indict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for ſuch an Image, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Whereupon finding Mr. <hi>Hunter</hi> my Partener Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warden, and he telling me alſo of it, we both reſolved to get a Copy of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictment, in order whereunto I went preſently to Mr. <hi>Tanner</hi> Clerk of the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:98858:3"/>Peace; and there and then I firſt ſaw and heard read the Indictment, and went and took advice what to do, and I was adviſed to end the matter as ſoon and as privately as I could, and to make the leaſt noiſe abroad about it, leſt the World ſhould think there was more in the thing than really there was. And I was advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed that the Monday after being the 7th. day of <hi>March</hi> there would be a private Seſſions, no concourſe of people, nor Juries, &amp;c. it being held chiefly on occaſion of reading a Pardon to ſome Priſoners, and ſo it would be beſt to go then and tell the Court how it was, and ſo make as good an end as I could, without ſpending the Pariſh Money about a rotten Image.</p>
               <p>Now though I had ſeen the Indictment on Friday, yet it was Saturday night nine of the clock before I could get a Copy thereof, and on Sunday morning I ſhewed it to my Partner Mr. <hi>Hunter</hi> and then ſent it to my Friend with whom I adviſed to peruſe, to whom I went in the Evening, and had the ſame advice as before; but I and my Partner both together told the Doctor and Lecturer of the thing, on Sunday Afternoon, both before and after Sermon in the Veſtry Houſe, but could not ſhew them the Copy of the Indictment becauſe I had ſent it away, but told them the ſubſtance of the matter. Hereupon preſently the Doctor and Lecturer, and Mr. <hi>Clement</hi> as I am informed, went to Mr. <hi>Tanner,</hi> and ſaw the Indictment there themſelves; and after they had been there then that very Sunday Evening, late, Mr. <hi>Hunter</hi> and my ſelf both met at the Doctors Houſe, (hearing the Doctor had been at my Houſe to ask for me) and there the Doctor told us that he had been at Mr. <hi>Tanners,</hi> and had ſeen the Indictment, and in his opinion we might defend our ſelves well enough, for the Indictment he thought was grounded upon an old Act that was made in <hi>Edw.</hi> VI. time, which he thought was onely againſt ſome certain Books and Images then in being and ſtanding, and particularized in that Act; and that this Image was ſo far from being ſtanding and being in thoſe times, that it was well known it was ſet up but about 20 years ago. Beſides, the Doctor told us another defence we might make, <hi>viz.</hi> that it is indicted by the name of <hi>S. Michael,</hi> and every one in Court (ſaid the Doctor) that hath ſeen <hi>S. Michael</hi> pictured, knows that <hi>S. Michael</hi> is always pictured with a Dragon under him, and this hath no Dragon; therefore let them prove it to be <hi>S. Michael,</hi> and that it was ever called <hi>S. Michael</hi> before. Furthermore the Doctor ſaid, we need not go till next Seſſions, and that we were beſt to call a Veſtry, and conſult then what to do in it.</p>
               <p>Hereupon I told the Doctor, that ſeeing it is a <hi>great, guilacd, carved Image,</hi> it will look as if we had a mind to defend Images, to plead that it is not <hi>S. Michael,</hi> or that it is not an Image meant by that Act, becauſe our Image was made ſince that Act. Beſides, the advice I have is, that that Act was made againſt all Images, and hath ſundry Clauſes in it that look to the future, and the <hi>Proviſo</hi> is againſt us, which provides for the ſtanding and remaining onely of ſuch Pictures as are upon Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Tombs, &amp;c. Therefore whether this be <hi>S. Michael</hi> or not it is all one, for the Act (as we are adviſed) may charge us with ſuffering the ſtanding and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a Carved Image of <hi>S. Michael,</hi> or ſome other Saint, or pretended or reputed Saint; therefore it may reach us, and for this reaſon we will go to morrow to Seſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and make the beſt defence we can, and hope we ſhall do well enough, becauſe neither you nor we did ſet it up; and therefore what ſhould you or we trouble our ſelves by Traverſing, to ſpend a great deal of Money to defend <hi>a great ſilly Image.</hi> We cannot call a Veſtry now it is night, and we'll go to morrow and quit our hands this Seſſions if we can, for I ſhall be out of my Office of courſe before another Seſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and I will try to rid our ſelves of it before I go out of my Office if poſſible, and hope to end it without you, ſo as you nor we may not have any further trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Then the Doctor replied, If you reſolve to go then I will go with you, or meet you there at Seſſions to morrow at two a clock.</p>
               <p>Thus with this Reſolution we parted, and then Mr. <hi>Hunter</hi> and my ſelf did both of us reſolve to go next day to Seſſions, and appointed to meet at <hi>Elfords</hi> Coffee Houſe at two a clock; but in the mean time conſidering what our Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor had told us, that every one in Court would judge this not to be <hi>S. Michael,</hi>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:98858:3"/>becauſe he had no Dragon under him; I thought the beſt way would be to carry I to Court to ſhew it, that they might judge by view, and accordingly on Monday at Noon-day, I took Mr. <hi>Graves</hi> our Pariſh Carpenter, and <hi>John Randal</hi> our Sex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, and <hi>Eliſton</hi> our Grave-maker, and a Porter, and no body elſe, and took the Image down, the Clerk was not there, nor knew any thing (as I verily believe) of taking it down, or of carrying it to Seſſions, untill after it was gone, nor was Mr. <hi>Hunter</hi> at the taking of it down, or knew it was down till he did ſee it, yet did I not take it down or carry it away otherwiſe privily, ſave only ſo as to prevent making a noiſe; And therefore I put it into a Decent, Clean, White Porters Bag, all but the Arm and Trumpet, which being made to take off at the Shoulder, and ſtanding out ſo far, that it would not go into Bag, I took off that, and <hi>John Randall</hi> car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed that under his Coat, and the Porter carryed the reſt in his bag on his Back. I called Mr. <hi>Hunter</hi> at <hi>Elford</hi>'s Coffee-houſe near Lombard-ſtreet, and told him I had brought the Image with me in a Porters Bag; and <hi>He</hi> and <hi>I</hi> and <hi>John Randal</hi> went thence in a Coach to Seſſions, and I ſhew'd Mr. <hi>Hunter</hi> in the Coach, that part of the <hi>Image</hi> which <hi>John Randal</hi> had under his Coat, and <hi>I</hi> alſo ſhew'd him the Porter, and told him there is the <hi>Image;</hi> and <hi>I</hi> carry it, that the Doctor may help us to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend it by thoſe Arguments he uſed to us laſt night; we will ſhew the thing to the Court, and ſo make an end without further trouble.</p>
               <p>When we came to Seſſions-houſe, Mr. <hi>Hunter</hi> and <hi>I</hi> both agreed not to carry it into Court, Except there ſhould be occaſion, but placed it in an outward room. Soon after we were at Seſſions, the Doctor (according to his promiſe) came and the Clerk with him; the Doctor ſeemed angry, that the Image was brought; I told him, that Remembring his Arguments laſt night was the reaſon I had brought it, that ſo the Court might ſee it had no Dragon under it, that ſo whether the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor had come or not, we might make a full demonſtration by the ſight, the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor told me we might remove it into the Crown Office, and there it might ly till the real Saints came indeed.</p>
               <p>But I ſtill told him I would, if I could end the matter now, becauſe I ſhould go out of my Office before another Seſſions; then the Doctor and both Mr. <hi>Hunter</hi> and <hi>I</hi> went into Court and ſat all three down together about half an Hour by Mr. <hi>Tanne<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> juſt by Sheriff <hi>Bethel;</hi> till at length a little before the cauſe came on, the Doctor was pleaſed to withdraw, and went quite away out of the Court without giving any reaſon to us, that I remember; but though the Doctor had thus deſerted us, we ſtill ſtay'd to make the beſt defence we could, and when the cauſe came on, we told the Court, that it had been ſet up on the Dial on the inward ſide of the Steeple at the weſt end of the Church, between two fret work figures of Death and Time, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 1659/60. by Mr. <hi>Edwards,</hi> when he was upper Church-Warden; Being asked, why it was removed, and ſet over the Altar or Communion-Table upon the Commandments, and when and who removed it; we told the Court it was done about <hi>Anno</hi> 75 or 76. by Mr. <hi>Clements,</hi> who was then upper Church-Warden, and not by us, and we ſuppoſed it was occaſioned to be removed, (as Mr. <hi>Clements</hi> told us) upon ſetting up the Organ, becauſe it could not ſo well be ſeen. We alſo told the Court it ſtood there ſo many years and had done no miracle, therefore we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived it could not be a Saint; then it being ſaid by ſome in Court, that the Image was without, it was called for in Court, and there it was viewed, and after both of us had ſaid further what we could in its defence, the Doctor having deſerted both us and the Image, who if he had ſtayed, it may be could have defended it better; and Mr. <hi>Tanner</hi> telling us, this diſcourſe will not do, you muſt either plead Gulity or not Guilty, or traverſe, or to ſuch purpoſe, and being told that to traverſe orremove it into the Crown Office, might coſt us Fifteen or Twenty Pound before we could end the Buſineſs that way, and being alſo told, that to confeſs would be but a ſine of Ten Shillings a piece, and ſo there would be a full end for us; thereupon <hi>I</hi> ſaid we cannot plead not Guilty, as to ſuch an Image ſtanding, and being in our Church, for here it is, and we muſt confeſs that it is true, this Image hath ſtood in our
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:98858:4"/>Church, and I brought him now from over the Communion Table, I pul'd it down from the Commandments, and it is a carved Image, it is in vain to deny it, or to ſpend money out of the Pariſh ſtock to defend it by removing it into the Crown O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ffice, or troubling our ſelves further about it; there it is, take it and do what you will with it; but Mr. <hi>Tanner</hi> ſtill inſiſting, that we muſt either ſay the word Guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty or not Guilty, then with one conſent both of us ſaid the very word, Guilty, and ſo it was recorded (as Mr. <hi>Tanner</hi> aſſured me) that both of us pleaded Guilty to the Indictment, not Mr. <hi>Sherman</hi> ſingly, as Mr. <hi>Sanders</hi> ſuggeſted, the Record will not miſ-report, whatever Mr. <hi>Banders</hi> may pleaſe to Print; And this pleading Guilty was done by both of us for no other Reaſon, but purely upon advice, that this Courſe was beſt, and would make leaſt noiſe, and be leaſt charge to the Pariſh; and we had really no ill intent, or any other end in all that is done by us, but for ſaving charges, and preventing noiſe and clamours, and believe, it might have ſo ceaſed, if Mr. <hi>Sanders</hi> had not put out two Narratives, for which he ought to have a double reprehenſion by us: <hi>Firſt,</hi> for printing Pariſh Matters without order of Veſtry, or the Dr. (or both Churchwardens, or the Upper-Churchwarden (ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gly) with Mr. <hi>Sanders</hi> his good leave) And <hi>Secondly</hi> for printing an untruth not only againſt your Churchwarden, but againſt the Clerk alſo; thus in time, he will ſet us all together by the Ears: I have been ever civil to Mr. <hi>Sanders,</hi> he hath been free at my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>able, both here and in the Country, and I had never any diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence with him, I pay him voluntarily as much as I pay the Dr., which is ten ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings a year, as Captain <hi>Burdon,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Barthwait,</hi> who Collect his money for him will teſtifie: and therefore I wonder at his unkind dealing with me, yet I ſhould ſtill have as great a value for Mr. <hi>Sanders,</hi> as ever I had, if he would leave Pariſh-Matters to us; to whom, I am adviſed, they much more properly belong than it doth to him to ſcrible thus againſt his Pariſhioners. He uſed to tell us every one ſhould mind his own buſineſs, but you ſee he does not practiſe ſo.</p>
               <p>When we had pleaded guilty, ſome cryed, knock it to pieces, burn it, but then I prayed, that I might have it to burn in our Veſtry, it would ſave us ſo much Billet; for we make a Fire there, every time there is a Sermon or meeting of Pariſhioners in cold weather, and I ſaid I would knock it to pieces, and burn it in the Veſtry, and the Court ſhould hear no more of it: Some in the Court, ſaid well, well, it is beſt ſo to do; it is true, I did not receive any written, or other order of Court for bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning it, but this ſaying well, well, it is beſt ſo to do, I took as conſent, and did then, and ſtill think it beſt ſo to do. The Court finding us ſubmitting, were pleaſed to ſay they would conſider of the Fine, or to ſuch effect; <hi>Interim,</hi> we paid nothing in Court, but ten ſhillings a piece to Mr. <hi>Tanner</hi> for Fees: Mr. <hi>Wil. Stevens</hi> of <hi>Green<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wich</hi> offered to buy it to ſet in his Garden; Mr. <hi>William Bullivant</hi> a known, eminent Broker on the <hi>Exchange,</hi> who buys Goods for Foreign Merchants, came to me, (when the Clerk was preſent) and told me he came to buy it to Ship beyond Sea, or words to that effect; others offered to buy it for ſcandalous uſes; no body ever offered (that I know of) to buy it to ſet it in a Church, as Mr. <hi>Sanders</hi> hints; it may be he might ſend ſome body to ſuch purpoſe, but I never ſpoke with any ſuch, that I can remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber; it was begged of Mr. <hi>Hunter,</hi> and I, indeed in Court by one, (who I ſuſpect would rather ſet it in a Baudy Houſe, than a Church) but I as well as Mr. <hi>Hunter</hi> both refuſed to give it away; and both of us ordered the Porter to carry it back in his Bag, and to lay it in ſome p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ivate Corner in the Church, which was done according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and I reckoned ſo ſoon as we made the next fire, to cut it in pieces, and burn it in the Veſtry, as I had promiſed in Court.</p>
               <p>This was <hi>Monday,</hi> but we had no occaſion of Fire there, before <hi>Sunday</hi> following, for the Miniſter or my ſelf was at payment of the poor; but on Wedneſday morning one came to tell me that I ſhould be indicted again for letting it remain in the Church undemoliſh'd; I told him, pray ſtay Sir, and I will fetch it, and you ſhall ſee it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moliſh'd which was accordingly done, and hath been ſince burnt at ſundry times at Veſtry meetings, and at payment of the poor: the laſt Log of it being burnt in the Veſtry on <hi>Good Friday.</hi> Now Gentlemen, Mr. <hi>Sanders</hi> having put out two <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paritions</hi>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:98858:4"/>already, what wold he have done if I had ſould it, might he not by Art-Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gick have filled the world with more new <hi>Apparitions</hi> in a Fortnights time, than he gives us new Sermons in a <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> for though he ſays in his laſt Scrible, Here is the end, yet he intimates, there is more a coming.</p>
               <p>O, But now Gentlemen, you will ſay, I have done this thing without order of Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, verily it is true, and I can't find but that one Churchwarden, <hi>viz.</hi> Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> ſet it up for his fancy without order of Veſtry for this particular Image above twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty years ago, and another Churchwarden, <hi>viz.</hi> Mr. <hi>Clements</hi> removed it to the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar about five years ago, without order of Veſtry; and I being firſt indicted for let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it ſtand ſo long, have now burnt it even likewiſe without order of Veſtry, for as the Learned Textuary, Mr. <hi>Sanders</hi> ſays, the Wiſe Man tells us, <hi>there is a time for all things;</hi> and I believe I have done as well in pulling it down, as they in ſetting it up, and indeed as I ought to do, when Images become ſo publickly offenſive, as you know of late this hath been, and meerly becauſe Mr. <hi>Sanders,</hi> and not the Doctor, make ſo many Reverend Bows before it, and began ſo lately other Ceremonies juſt under it, eſpecially, if you conſider that Mr. <hi>Sanders</hi> never ſaid theſe Services, and Benedicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons at the Altar, or Bowed, before the Image was ſet there.</p>
               <p>And thus as to the Narrative of Fact, as Mr. <hi>Sanders</hi> phraſeth it,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Here is the end.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I will acknowledg, that in ſome Drolling Diſcourſes at Coffee-Houſes, and elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where upon this Matter, I may have rendred ſome of theſe Tranſactions in other ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions; but this Account here now penn'd, is as to matter of Fact the truth, the whole truth, and nothing but the truth, to the beſt of my memory; or if I have va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried is any expreſſions, or minute circumſtances, I ſhall be more ready to acknowledg and rectifie it, then I do yet find Mr. <hi>Sanders</hi> to be. <hi>Interim,</hi> I do affirm, that the ſubſtance of the matter, is to the effect aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>Thus far; Gentlemen, I have gone ſeriouſly on, and now according to the Mode of diſpatching buſineſs in our Pariſh, lets go to the Tavern, and merrily diſcourſe what all of us can ſay farther about this matter. There may poſſibly be ſome amongſt you of that tender-natur'd, ſimpathizing humour as to be a little heated at ſight of this poor Image in Flames, and ready to quench them with compaſſionate Tears, or at leaſt that have a months mind to put the Pariſh into a flame of diſputes about it, under a notion of defending it, by calling it an Ornament of the Church, and ſo that way de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend, <hi>Great Guilded, Carved Images,</hi> Let ſuch Gentlemen take their Courſe, for I give this Account only to relate the truth, not in the leaſt to preclude (as Mr. <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> hath it) you or any body from any Legal Porſecution againſt me for what I have done either ſingly or joyntly with my Partner.</p>
               <p>But Doctor and Gentlemen, be pleaſed to compare this with Mr. <hi>Sanders</hi> his two <hi>Pamphlets</hi> of <hi>Apparitions;</hi> and do you and the World judg. what untruth he hath rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and what reaſon we have to defend ſuch a mighty <hi>Carved, Guilded Image</hi> with an argument that it is not againſt that Act, or that it is not St. <hi>Michael.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Gentlemen, you all cannot but know what hath given the occaſion to indict us for this Image, <hi>viz.</hi> Becauſe they ſay that in our Pariſh, we are making ſteps to ſomething that I won't name, becauſe I won't believe it; but that our ſteps have been thus cannot be denied, <hi>viz.</hi> Firſt in 75 We ſet up a ſtately and chargeable pair of Organs, and in 77 we beautified them, and we ſet upon our Altar this Image, which they knick-named Saint <hi>Michael:</hi> (and Pamphleteers ſay, the Rhemiſh Annotations call him next to Chriſt, and the Son of God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) and when we had got Saint <hi>Michael</hi> up, then in 77 Mr. <hi>Whitebread</hi> (a Kinſman of that father <hi>Whitebread,</hi> that was hang'd for the damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Popiſh Plot) he gives us a rich Crimſon Carpet with a brave em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broidered Glory of the Sun upon it, with a Croſs with this Inſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the Margin, and as ſoon as we had this we took up our clean white Linnen Cloath which the Act of Conformity directs ſhould be uſed, and which we covered the Table formerly with, on Communion Days, ſo
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:98858:5"/>as our Linnen Cloath hung down to the ground in the Weſt Front of our Communion Table; nay People would perſwade us, our Communion Table looks like an Altar, Becauſe it ſtands the Altar faſhion, with ends, North and South, as the Papiſts do ſet theirs, Joyning cloſe to the Commandments, ſo that we cauſe the back part or Eaſt ſide of our Linnen to be tackt up about a foot or more above the Table, faſtening it to the Commandments, and they further alledge, that the Act of Conformity does not direct the tacking it up thus to the Altar, for ſome ſay, that by the Act of Uniforminy it may be allowed for the Table to ſtand a yard off from the Commandments in the Chancel, eſpecially in our Chancel, becauſe there is room enough to ſtand ſo in the inward ſide of the Rails; Nay, they ſay that the Communion-Table may by that very Act ſtand in the Body of the Church, and then, they ſay, it would not look ſo like an Altar; they ſay that inſtead of the clean white Linnen of our Mother Church we ſhew now nothing in our front, but this new glorious rich Crimſon gift of Mr. <hi>Whitebread,</hi> and we have regiſtred it in our Table hanging in our Veſtry by the Title of one of our Church Ornaments, ſo that they reproach us and ſay, we have turned up the clean white Tippet of our vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Mother; (meaning the white Linnen, which the Act of Uniformity directs we ſhould uſe) and foulded the forepart of our Linnen now on the Table, on purpoſe to ſhew in our front ſuch rich Embroidery, as is not appointed by the ſaid Act.</p>
               <p>They further tell us not only (that we ſay ſecond ſervice, at this Communion-Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble or Altar) but that Mr. <hi>Sanders</hi> as ſoon as Sermon is ended gives neither Prayer nor bleſſing in the Pulpit, but ſtops the ſervice of God by cauſing the Organ to ſtrike up a Tune to divert the People until he goes into Veſtry to put on his Surplice, which Occaſioned the people to ſay, what ſhall we have no Bleſſing! whither goes the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter? By and by he comes out of the Veſtry; ſo habited, mounts the ſteps, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters the Rails; then at his approach towards the middle of the Altar, he makes a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal bow before it, then he turns to the North-end and kneels, then the people cry, whither goes he now? But there he ſays ſome prayers, ſometime more, ſometime leſs, as he pleaſeth, and then pronounceth the Bleſſing at the Altar, which uſeth to be done in the Pulpit; now they confidently ſay, theſe are things never practized ſince the Kings happy Reſtoration in our Church; they add, that Mr. <hi>Sanders</hi> never went up to ſay ſecond ſervice, nor ſervice or a bleſſing after Sermon, nor ever bow'd ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept on Sacrament days, when the bread, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> was there. Before we had got up Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans in 75. beautified them in 77. ſet this great carved Guilded Image on the top of the Altar and Commandments, and got Mr. <hi>Whitebread</hi>'s Glorious Cope or Carpet; and that Mr. <hi>Sanders</hi> was the firſt beginner of theſe bowing Ceremonies and other Services and Benedictions after Sermon at the Altar, in Doctor <hi>Layfields</hi> time, and that he urged Doctor <hi>Layfield</hi> to let him begin the ſame: Soon after we were prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with, and had got together all this furniture, which, were begun by Mr. <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> juſt about the time the Helliſh Popiſh Plot broke out, though Doctor <hi>Lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field</hi> diſwaded him from begining thoſe Ceremonies at ſuch a juncture, ſaying, O Mr. <hi>Sanders!</hi> what will the world ſay of us? that we ſhould begin ſuch Ceremonies but juſt now, (which was about the time the Popiſh Lords were ſent to the <hi>Tower</hi>) why ſhould we be more forward juſt now in our Ceremonies than others? were we not blam'd for it in Forty one, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or to ſome ſuch effect. But Mr. <hi>Sanders</hi> reylyed, none but a few inconſiderable people would be offended at it, and therefore he would then Uſher in theſe Ceremonies, and did accordingly do it.</p>
               <p>Now Gentlemen we can't ſay, but all theſe things are very true in Subſtance or to ſuch effect, and it is generally known in the Pariſh, as alſo by ſtrangers to be ſo, for they may read it on our Organs thus made, 75. beautified, 77. and in a Table hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in our Veſtry, <hi>in hac verba</hi> 
                  <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> Mr. <hi>Thomas Whitebread</hi> Citizen and Cloth-worker of <hi>London</hi> gave in his life-time, in the Year one Thouſand ſix Hundred ſeventy ſeven, a Rich Crimſon Velvet Communion Carpet, with a Rich Glory Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broidered thereon in Gold, and a Gold and Silk fringe about the ſame Carpet, alſo a Crimſon Velvet Cuſhion with four Golden Toſſels to it, and a <hi>Portugal Mat</hi> to lie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Communion Table.</p>
               <p>Nor can we deny but that Mr. <hi>Sanders</hi> was the firſt that brought up the Uſe of theſe
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:98858:5"/>Ceremonies in our Church, and that they never were practized until after this Great Carved Guilded Image was mounted on the top of the Altar, and untill we had Mr. <hi>Whitebread</hi>'s glorious Carpet to ſpread the ſame. Gentlemen, Pray conſider theſe things; I wiſh we could deny any one of theſe matters, and that we could ſay any one Syllable of them in Subſtance were falſe, and then we might deſire our Doctor to print an anſwer in our Vindication, and ſo Satisfye, or at leaſt Contradict the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that thus talk of us.</p>
               <p>And really Doctor, if you do not anſwer and defend us, I fear our Lecturer can't; yet it would credit him much to let it come out in his name, and it would ſerve our purpoſe too; for then if any error be found in it, we may only ſay (as formerly in other errors in his Apparitions) his hand did ſhake when he writ it, and that the Doctor ſhall mend it next time.</p>
               <p>As to the anſwer, that I would have Mr. <hi>Sanders</hi> give to the world, pray under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand me, I would have him ſay, not only why we do theſe things, for he hath poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly got an anſwer very ready, by pretending that the Rubrick directs it ſo to be done, but if he puts his name to it, they will at him in Print again, with Queries, which I would fain prevent; and therfore I humbly propoſe Doctor, that the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer may prevent Scurvey Queries, therefore in our anſwer, let us give invinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble reaſons, why we did never ſay ſo much as Second-Service, much leſs our Sermon Service and Benediction, nor perform theſe Ceremonies exactly as we do, before now of late? And why Mr. <hi>Sanders</hi> never bowed there before? and who Mr. <hi>Sanders</hi> doth bow to? whether it be to the Image? or the Carpet? and to whom or why he bows at all in that place and that way, rather than in any other place, or other way in the Church? and he muſt give a particular reaſon, why the Doctor doth never bow at all, no, not at Sacrament days? And why Mr. <hi>Sanders</hi> bowes only juſt two times in a Fore-noon, and never in an afternoon? and why he doth not bow before he enters the Rails, and alſo when he paſſes by the Rails and Altar, as, they ſay, other very great Clergy-men do in Cathedrals, and ſome Chappels; And alſo we muſt anſwer why we account <hi>White-bread</hi>'s Carpet a better Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment than our own Linnen; for if it be not better, they will ſay we are Fools, for uſeing of it, for we ought to uſe the very beſt, elſe other Churches may be more regularly devout then we.</p>
               <p>And then Mr. <hi>Sanders</hi> muſt anſwer for the Carved Image, which he calls Mr. <hi>Sher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi>'s God-ſon, for in my conſcience <hi>I</hi> am not obliged to anſwer for him, becauſe <hi>I</hi> was not his Godfather; and if Mr. <hi>Sanders</hi> will not help me out with this Job, I will never be Godfather as long as I live to any dull Saint or Angel of them all, nor to no man, wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, or child; if the Brats muſt be laid to me, the Pope ſhall be Godfather to all the Images you ſhall ſet up, for all me.</p>
               <p>It is true, all the Children laid in our Pariſh, the Upper Churchwarden provides for the Brats, and does give them what name he pleaſe, but I made the Grave maker and any Beggar be the Godfather and Godmother, (becauſe we muſt have Godfathers and Godmothers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) I gave them a Pot of Ale for their pains, and ſo parted; let theſe Beggars look out for their God-children, if they will, for all me, for I do not find my Oath obliged my care longer than I am in my Office; nor do I find them prove ſuch forward Brats to ſpeak in a year;</p>
               <p>Though the Poet in a Play tells us,
<q>
                     <l>Where Parents are Slaves</l>
                     <l>Their Brats can't be any other;</l>
                     <l>Great Wits and Great Braves</l>
                     <l>Had always a Pug to their Mother.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>But I think there muſt be theſe farther Anſwers to the Image; what need have we of any Images at all in our Churches? prove that firſt ſubſtantially, and then what kind of Images, whether of Saints or Angels, or Chriſt on the Croſs, or Fryars, or Benefactors, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But pray enlarge much upon our Benefactor's Images; for I find by experience they bring moſt money to our Church; and that the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:98858:6"/>Benevolence of them is the beſt maintenance we have for our Poor: and by my Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count it will appear, that we have had much more mony come in from our deceaſed Benefactor, than I and my Parther, and two Sideſmen, and <hi>Eliſton,</hi> and loud <hi>John Bounick</hi> have got in two years bawling, all ſix of us at the door, Thus, <hi>pray remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the poor, pray remember the poor;</hi> there ore let us have all our Benefactors Pictures bravely carved and guilded, as like as ever one Pea was like another; this may encourage more Benefactors; and if the Anſwer be well penn'd to that point, it may be worth all the Tithes, <hi>Eaſter</hi> Offerings, and Lecture-mony too that we pay you.</p>
               <p>My relating how far Mr. <hi>Hunter</hi> acted, is only to ſatisfie you how falſly the Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlets of Mr. <hi>Sanders</hi> have repreſented the matter in print to the world: not in the leaſt to vindicate my ſelf by having had Mr. <hi>Hunter</hi>'s conſent; for what Mr. <hi>Hunter</hi> acted, was but as the Under-Churchwarden uſeth often to gowith the Upper-Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warden as his Aſſiſtant; therefore if any juſt blame be for what is done, I had rather bear all the blame and dammage too that can happen, than ſuffer any body ſo much as to think ill of Mr. <hi>Hunter</hi> from any one part of this matter; I have only this to ſay, that we both did think we did for the beſt; and I ſay again I believe it will prove ſo.</p>
               <p>For this reaſon, becauſe the more noiſe and pother Mr. <hi>Sanders</hi> hath made about it, the more it may by ſome be ſuſpected that Mr. <hi>Sanders</hi> would willingly defend Images in Churches, becauſe he lays ſo much blame on a Churchwarden for not defending them no better, and for not calling a Veſtry to conſult how to do it, or how to delay the Proceedings till another Seſſions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But I do conceive, that I may account the burning of this Image (after all Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances conſidered) no more Sacriledg, than burning an old Broom that belongs to the Church; and ſhall be of that mind, until Mr. <hi>Sanders</hi> do convince the contrary in print; That this Image hath been more dedicated or conſecrated at firſt, or ſince, to the Church, than all the Brooms every Churchwarden hath paid for ſince the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage was made; now it doth concern him to tell the world why he made this Text his ſubject for the firſt Pamphlet, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thou that abhorreſt Idols, doſt thou commit Sacriledg? If <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h do not prove my burning this Image to be Sacriledg, then he si beſides the Text; but <hi>I</hi> will grant that the Desk hath been more conſecrated than the Image; but <hi>I</hi> do not know how much the Clerks place in the Desk is leſs conſecrated than the Readers place in the ſame D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>sk; <hi>I</hi> anſwer they are both in one and the ſame Desk, they both ſit jig by joul together, not an Inch between; nay, the Clerk's place is on the Reader's right hand; alſo the Clerk's place is nearer the Pulpit than the Readers, ſo that the Lecturer can't go up into the Pulpit, but (if he be civil) he muſt ſay by your leave Mr. Clerk.</p>
               <p>Therefore all theſe things conſidered, <hi>I</hi> find little reaſon for Mr. <hi>Sanders</hi> when he had done Reading Prayers in the Desk lately, to fall out with the poor Clerk for ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding up (where Mr. <hi>Sanders</hi> had ſtood) to publiſh a Veſtry; and to ſay Sirrah this place is more conſecrated than yours; and Sirrah your Shoes are not clean enough to ſtand up here: Lord bleſs us, to what height will this ceremonious Lecturer bring us; becauſe the Clerk and Mr. <hi>Sanders</hi> can't ſet their Horſes together: muſt we ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer him to print <hi>Sham Pamphlets</hi> without order of Veſtry; and ſo ſpread falſe Stories about the Pariſh to ſet you and me and all the Pariſh into heats and differences: well if it were poſſible for him to make you and all the whole Pariſh fall out with me, yet he ſhall never be able to make me fall out with you; for <hi>I</hi> will not ſo much as be angry at any proſecution you can think of; for <hi>I</hi> am aſſured that at any Tavern-meeting with you or any man elſe with whom <hi>I</hi> have any difference, the very firſt Glaſs of Wine will waſh away the greateſt grumbling, that ever <hi>I</hi> had in my Gizard; and render me fully reconcil'd; therefore let us have another merry meeting at Tavern, and let Mr. <hi>Sanders</hi> be there; and let us laugh and droll out thoſe Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and drink healths roundly, as we did bravely, when we din'd at the Vine Tavern at our late Election day; and pledg me in a full Glaſs, and drink Confuſion to the Pope and all his Party, from <hi>Dan</hi> to <hi>Beerſheba;</hi> let there be no man in our Pariſh have any other diſtinction, but Proteſtant or Papiſt, for could all that are Proteſtants but truly love and agree one with another we need not fear Pope, nor Monſieur: O,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:98858:6"/>then we ſhould be a moſt ſerious regularly devout Pariſh indeed. Mr. <hi>Sanders</hi> hath one fling at me more about my Proceedings in Veſtry. He hath a mighty opinion of himſelf; can't that pleaſe him which the Doctor or Veſtry have printed nothing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt; yet when they do, I will not only ſay, but make it appear, even by the Lord Biſhops own Grant, that they cannot hold a Veſtry without both or at leaſt one of the Churchwardens; and if one Churchwarden be not at it, it is but a Junto of a Veſtry. Let the Laity keep the power in the hands of their Churchwardens, for what they yield (perhaps but out of reſpect) to a Proteſtant Vicar, it will be claimed, if Popery comes in, as due to a Popiſh <hi>Vicar;</hi> for all Popiſh Succeſſors that ſhall come into our Living, will expect rather more than leſs, than was yielded by us Hereticks, as they will call us.</p>
               <p>But I am ſo ſatisfied in what I have done relating both to the Image and Veſtry, that I ſhall not need to fear to ſubmit the whole matter, nay any other difference I may happen to have with any one in the world, to the Cenſure of our Dioceſan himſelf, to whom as my duty I owe and ſhall pay as great Veneration, as any of you all.</p>
               <p>But furthermore, I pray forget not likewiſe to anſwer, why we call an Image an Ornament either to the Church or Commandments; for we dare not call ſuch a great carved guilded Image as this is, an Ornament to the Commandments of God in a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Church; for Images are directly contrary to one of thoſe very Commandments. And why we ſhould ſuffer this Image to ſtand upon the Commandments of God, juſt as if it were ready with its feet to kick that Commandment out of our number as ſoon as ever Popery ſhall enter, for we know that Papiſts leave that out of their Decalogue. There are a world more things we muſt anſwer if you will keep Images in our Church; for what will it avail us to ſay, that it is not St. <hi>Michael,</hi> for they will ſay it is an I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage? And what good will it do us to plead, that it is not againſt the old Act of <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> VI. for if theſe Pleas might have brought us off at the <hi>Old Baily;</hi> yet it will not prove Images to be Ornaments to Proteſtant Churches, for there is a much older Law made at Mount <hi>Sinai</hi> againſt it.</p>
               <p>And therefore truely in my ſimple judgment, Doctor and Gentlemen, we ought to blame him that let up this Image on the Steeple, and him that removed it to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments, rather than him that pull'd it down and burnt it. Pray what was the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion in the primitive times of Images? and what is your opinion of them?</p>
               <p>In ſober ſadneſs, are we not all to blame that when the Doct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r and Mr. <hi>Sanders</hi> and Mr. <hi>Clements</hi> and others of us heard that there was a complaint of offence it had given the Seſſions before, (which by the way Mr. <hi>Sanders</hi> ſeeming willing to forget) that we did not burn it preſently, before we had been thus ſhamefully talk'd on for it; and now for any one of you to tell the world that you will proſecute me in the Biſhops Court, for deſtroying of ſuch a filthy ſubbardly Image, under pretence of waſting Church-Goods, and calling it an Ornament, after I had been indicted for letting it ſtand ſo long; really, Gentlemen, if you are not aſhamed of ſuch Imprudence; I bluſh for you, and am ſo charitable as to believe, that when you are more cool you will be more wiſe. Single me out, any man of you, or Doctor and all of you toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that can convince me or any man living (but a <hi>Tory</hi> or <hi>Papiſt</hi>) that ſuch a great carved Image is any Ornament at all to a Chriſtian Church, where God will be worſhiped in Spirit and Truth, and adds the leaſt force to the Commandments of God, and then to recompence you for loſs of this one fuſty Image, I will ſet you up as many Images as there are Commandments.</p>
               <p>Will not the World think that our wiſe Lecturer knew the very critical time when Popery was juſt approaching, and to ſhew his pious Zeal, juſt then begun to bow be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore an Image, and ſtill has the confidence to plead for an Image (by way of blaming the Church-warden for not conſulting the wiſdom of the Veſtry how to defend it better.)</p>
               <p>And that this Lecturer ſhould be ſo zealouſly forward as to go to Pariſhioners houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es with the Church-warden that was in 75, to ſtir up them and their Lodgers and Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers alſo to contribute Money towards bringing Organs into our Church in 75.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:98858:7"/>And that this Image ſhould be advanced from the Steeple and mounted on the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments.</p>
               <p>And that our Organs muſt be beautified in 77.</p>
               <p>And that Mr. <hi>Whitebreads</hi> Zeal ſhould be alſo juſt then ſtirred up in 77 to give us ſuch Rich furniture to our Altar, O mighty great foreſight in this deep Lecturer, that he ſhould nick the lucky Minute ſo well, to time it ſo near the coming out of the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Plot, that ſo we might plead we had theſe things in our Church before! A man would think he had conſulted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>her Provincial <hi>Whitebread</hi> his nown ſell in the timing it; eſpecially ſince Mr. <hi>Sanders</hi> hath a living at <hi>Sandon</hi> in <hi>Eſſex</hi> ſo near the Pariſh of <hi>Rittle</hi> on one hand, and the great Popiſh Family on the other hand, where this Father Provincial had his uſual Reſidence or Reſort.</p>
               <p>I do not know who was the Godfather of this Saint <hi>Michael,</hi> but a hundred of our Folks in this Pariſh will tell you, that Mr. <hi>Sanders</hi> was the firſt, that gave occaſion to be indicted upon account of Saint <hi>Michael;</hi> and that Mr. <hi>Sanders</hi> was the firſt, that bowed his body before him, and offered up Prayers under his Noſe.</p>
               <p>And for my part I am no other ways offended with the Ceremony my ſelf, but for that in our Church-warden's Pew, I could not hear the Prayers ſaid at the Altar, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that I have been asked by Strangers, whom I have let into that Pew, what is the Miniſter doing; Is he Churching of a Woman? And now we ſpeak of Women; the truth is, the Women in many parts, both of the South and North Iſles can neither ſee nor hear the Miniſter at the Altar; but perhaps it would be no great matter for the women, whether they hear or not, if we have the ſame Opinion of women here in <hi>England,</hi> that the <hi>Turks</hi> have of them. <hi>viz.</hi> That women have no Souls; But for my part I am a great <hi>Abhorror</hi> of that <hi>Mahometan, Turkiſh</hi> Opinon; for I do really believe that women are the fineſt Creatures and the beſt Souls in the whole World, a mighty pretty invention at firſt and the whole Race of mankind would ceaſe if we ſhould be deprived of that noble Sex; And therefore I am ſo mightily concerned for them, that I am and muſt be an <hi>Earneſt Petitioner</hi> to the Lord Biſhop, that our Church Prayers may be ſaid not only where women may hear, but alſo where they may all ſee and be ſeen by us.</p>
               <p>When I tell Mr. <hi>Sanders</hi> that we cannot hear, he anſwers, what have you Books for? nay then quoth I, if Books will ſerve turn, what need we Parſons? When you go up to the Altar, let ſome go down to the Font, and pray to themſelves and others be turned into Cabals, whiſpering together as ſome do, or let us pray privately, thus to our ſelves, <hi>Lord hear us, for we can't hear the Parſon.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Libera nos Domine,</hi>
               </q>
               <q>For no Parſon can we ſee.</q>
               <p>Really Gentlemen, theſe things ought to be conſidered by us; and we ought moſt humbly to beſeech our Lord the Biſhop, that we may have our ſervices, prayers, and benedictions all ſaid in the Desk and Pulpit again, as we uſed to have till this Damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Helliſh Popiſh Plot broke out, that we may all know what the Parſon is doing, and ſo may all joyn together in ſaying <hi>Amen,</hi> as we ought to do; elſe prayers in La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin, or an unknown Tongue may do as much good as prayers that we can't hear: But yet God forbid, (though we don't underſtand a word he ſays) that ever we ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire him to alter his courſe without an Act of Parliament, if it be againſt Law.</p>
               <p>But I muſt tell you, Gentlemen, becauſe People can't hear, it drives many from our Pariſh; Church; ſhall we not have many Diſſenters at this rate and this ought to grieve us; for it pleaſes the Papiſts to ſee us begin more Ceremonies than we did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, they hope we will a ſtep further, and come home to them, and then they will ſay we are a regular, devout Pariſh indeed, as Mr. <hi>Sanders</hi> calls us.</p>
               <p>You will ſay, I have a great mind to be examining this Image, becauſe I muſt ſtill have this one touch more at him, why he ſhould ſtand Trumpetting there on the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments with his face towards the Organs; I find no reaſon upon Record in our
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:98858:7"/>Church Regiſters; but ſome late Expoſitors or Modern Caſuiſts in our Pariſh, ſay it is that Saint <hi>Michael</hi> may with his Trumpet reſpond to the Organs: Nay, ſome Learned men in the Act of Conformity, ſay the Act of Conformity does not forbid us with a Trumpet of Saint <hi>Michael</hi> to reſpond to the Organ; and Learned men (Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cturers of Mr. <hi>Saunders</hi> caſt always excepted) ſay that the Act of Conformity does not direct the People and Clark to Reſpond in the Reading Pſalms, but hold that it is <hi>Contra formam Statuti.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Well, what if ſome of it be contrary to Law, if yet we can ſay, it is <hi>Secundum uſum Sarum, Hereford, York, Bangor, Lincoln,</hi> or ſome or all of them, or if we can get it paſs unexamined, conclude, <hi>utrum horum mavis Accipe,</hi> Hab Nab at a venture?</p>
               <p>What matter is it, may we not ſay, all we do is Conformity, and as Mr. <hi>Saunders</hi> moſt elegantly phraſeth it, that there is not a more ſerious, and regulary devout Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh in this City of <hi>London</hi> then this of <hi>Alhallows Baerkin,</hi> is?</p>
               <p>Gentlemen, what ſhall I do? I diſpleaſed the Papiſts by pulling down one Image, but I pleaſe them again in promiſing them to ſet up ten for one; but I hope they will ſtay till the condition is fulfilled, that I am convinced they are Ornaments; and in my Conſcience Papiſts will ſooner make it out then Mr. <hi>Sanders:</hi> But then on the other ſide, I am envied by all kind of Phanaticks, and Quakers for my rigid Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, and for my forcing the Quakers to ſhut up their ſhops, at <hi>Chriſtmas</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther good days, inſomuch as we have not one Conventicle in all our Pariſh for fear of my proſecuting them; and after all this Out, and Alas! is it come to this, That you Doctor and Gentlemen of the Veſtry ſhould talk of proſecuting me for burning an I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage which you call your Ornament?</p>
               <p>O! Would I had never been Churchwarden; even ſhare and take the Office among you, who will, ſo as I may never be Churchwarden of this Pariſh more, as long as the Sun and Moon endure.</p>
               <p>But prry deal gently with me, becauſe I have had the Great Honour (as ſome of you are pleaſed to call it) to be Churchwarden of this Pariſh of <hi>All Saints Barkin London;</hi> which at this time, and on ſo <hi>laudable</hi> an occaſion, as an <hi>Image,</hi> is printed to be ſo regularly devout a Pariſh, but the Prints that calls it ſo, are both Titled an <hi>Apparition, &amp;c.</hi> and therefore I am afraid that we ſhall have but a little ſhare of that Honour, becauſe we pulled down and burnt a rotten Image; and behold the vain <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paritions</hi> both diſappear.</p>
               <p>But Doctor and Gentelemen, if all this will not ſatisfie you, then <hi>in verbo Guardani Eccleſiae,</hi> or in as plain Engliſh, as a Layman and an expiring: Churchwarden can utter at drawing out the laſt breath of his Office, who though he ought not to go out us he comes in ſwearing; yet I cannot forbear to ſay by the Oath of a Churchwarden, turn the Buckle of your Girdle behind you: For I challenge you to charge me with any undue exeution of my Office; and then for any other Foreign Matter, I care not what you ſay, for if it be any thing that does not belong to this Office, it will be thought not only impertinent, but malicious.</p>
               <p>As for Doctor <hi>Hicks,</hi> he came to our Pariſh upon the Death of Doctor <hi>Layfield</hi> but about eight months ago; I had the honour to give him his Induction, and he cannot charge me with any diſreſpect towards him. Theſe Ceremonies were begun by Mr. <hi>Sanders</hi> before Dr. <hi>Hicks</hi> came; and the Dr. finding them, is pleaſed to continue them, only the Dr. never Bows, and he is ſo kind to us, as to come from the Altar as far as the Rails to read ſome part of the Service, whereby we hear the Dr. better than Mr. <hi>Sanders,</hi> becauſe Mr. <hi>Sanders</hi> will not budg a foot, but keeps his ſtation at the North end of the Table. Thus the Dr. and Lecturer do diſſent from each other in perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of the Ceremonies: whereupon ſome late Prints have told us that men of leaſt Learning are for moſt Ceremonies.</p>
               <p>The blame now appears to lye upon Mr. <hi>Sanders</hi> for ſetting up ſuch Ceremanies at ſuch a juncture of time. And if blame alſo may lye upon all the Churchwadens that had a hand in ſetting up, or removing or burning this Image; Let every one then ſhew ſo good occaſion, for the part they have acted, as I have done for my part in pulling of it down and burning it. What if I had never been Indicted at Seſſions at all; might I not, nay, ought I not to have done it when it had given ſuch offences?</p>
               <p>The Organs ſtand on the Gallery a Conſiderable Diſtance from the Steeple, and Mr.
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:98858:8"/>
                  <hi>Clements</hi> had no Veſtry Order, to alter the Dyal on the Steeple, yet he did bring the Dial about 10 Foot forwarder then it was, and if ever be occaſion, any Jury, or any body elſe, may ſee he might have had room enough to have placed this Image again in a void ſpace of 10 foot ſquare between Death and Time, or juſt under Death or Time<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or in ſome other place there abouts, where it might have been conſpicuous enough, if the view were ſo eſſentially neceſſary, without taking ſo great a leap, as from the Stee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to the Chancel: and ſo as Mr. <hi>Sanders</hi> Phraſeth it (as to you.) <hi>Here is the End.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your Late Upper Church-warden: <hi>Edmond Sherman.</hi>
                  </signed>

               </closer>
               <postscript>
                  <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
                  <p>THIS <hi>Image</hi> was a <hi>Great, Carved, Guilded Image,</hi> and about a yard and half long, with great, broad, ſpreading Wings, each Wing about three quart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of a yard long; the right Arm and Hand was in its full proportion, holding a Trumpet near to its Mouth, the left hand appeared as it were, but juſt coming out of its ſhoulder, holding up the end of a Label of Lead, the other end of the Label hung down to his right foot: On the Label was wrote to this effect, <hi>Ariſe you dead, and come to Judgment;</hi> his face, hands and feet painted, all the reſt of it was guilded; It had no Dragon under it, yet in weight about 18 or 20 ſtone.</p>
                  <floatingText type="letter">
                     <body>
                        <opener>
                           <salute>Mr. <hi>Jonathan Sanders</hi> Lecturer:</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>Sir, In execution of my office of Churchwarden, having found two late Vagabond Brats in our Pariſh; Chriſtened (I ſuppoſe without any Canonical Goſſips) by the fright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful names of <hi>Apparitions;</hi> They are here brought home to your door, pray take your Brats again, you being Father and Godfather alſo to both. I find it alſo juſt to charge your late bowing Ceremonies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to be the Stallion that have occaſionally begot theſe Brats, and all this noiſe and pother; yet I have done it with as little perſonal reflection as to any Foreign Matter, as poſſibly I could; becauſe, for me or you to rail and rip up each others, only by bedaubing the other with ſtories, how true ſoever, yet impertinent to the Matter in hand; and ſo people would be apt to give no credit to his report that does ſo, therefore keep to the Matter. You call me the <hi>Guilty Churchwarden;</hi> ſuppoſe now that you ſhould plead not guilty at Seſſions; and ſuppoſe that by the Common Law you ſhould come off with that Plea, as to this Image ſtanding, and being in our Church, becauſe it may be more properly Churchwarden's buſineſs, to ſet up Images, than a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter's or Lecturer's buſineſs, to call them Ornaments; yet that will not convince the world, but that you are guilty of the occaſion of the Indictment, by the bowing and late Ceremonies begun at ſuch a juncture of Time when ſo many believe that Popery was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned to have entered about that time among.</p>
                        <p>Come unkind <hi>Jonathan,</hi> we all have our faults; and it is true, that neither I nor you, nor the Pope himſelf is infallible, therefore let us leave this Scribling, or elſe we ſhall ſoon be as much talked off as other Scriblers about Town. For my part I am for letting an honeſt Vintner take our money, rather than theſe miſchievous Bookſellers: and for your part you have declared (in your <hi>Apparitions</hi>) both againſt Liberty of Conſcience, and Liberty of the Preſs; therefore, ſince our humours jump ſo well, Let's to the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern, and there droll and laugh, and ſing merrily, Thus,
<q>
                              <l>Troubles and Fears are ne're to be found</l>
                              <l>But in the dull place where the Glaſs goes not round:</l>
                              <l>Let's caſt away Care, and hang up our Sorrow,</l>
                              <l>O come then Drink on,</l>
                              <l>Say he's a Jon—a—thon,</l>
                              <l>And a Sot that takes care for to morrow:</l>
                              <l>Store of good Clarot ſupplies every thing,</l>
                              <l>K—And the Man that's drunk, is as great as a—ing.</l>
                           </q>
                        </p>
                        <p>Thus in deſpight of the bookſellers, let us drink a little wine for the Stomach ſake, and let You and I be in a merry humour as long as we live.</p>
                        <p>Me-thoughts we were very merry at Tavern-dinner laſt Election day, <hi>ſecundium u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum Barkin;</hi> you know we had not one word there of this punch-gutted Image, but were moſt regularly merry and jolly; for after Churchwardens health had gone round, I drank the Doctor's health, and then <hi>I</hi> begun yours too Mr. <hi>Jonathan,</hi> and after that our Doctor begun his Grace the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury</hi>'s good health: and we
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:98858:8"/>had a general health to all the Royal Family at once, all which were carried on decently, and in order. For though it was ſomewhat contradictory to one of his Majeſtie's Proclamations to quaff healths at that rate, yet <hi>I</hi> did it for Conformity ſake; and <hi>I</hi> hope it will not be impured a violation of Law or Loyalty in ſuch Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Company: beſides, me-thoughts you and <hi>I</hi> were particularly merry, and <hi>I</hi> liked it well, becauſe it ſtill tended more fully to demonſtrate to all the world, that there is not a more ſerious and regularly devout Pariſh in all <hi>London,</hi> than our <hi>All-to be-Sainted Barkin,</hi> not only for Ceremonies, but alſo for good order in drinking: our Noble Capt. took indefatigable pains to put our Carrouzes into a ſtrict and regular method, by giving the neceſſary words of Command, as <hi>forbear firing, make all rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, each man cling Glaſſes, and then, Huzza, Ce viva vio Le Roy, &amp;c.</hi> And ſo our whole volley of Healths went off together bravely, all which being ſo Canonically performed, <hi>I</hi> hope for all the burning of Saint <hi>Michael</hi>'s Bones, our Renowned Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh ſhall not loſe an Inch of us Reputation, nor be cenſur'd as irregular, but ſhall ſtill remain as a primitive Pattern for all <hi>London,</hi> yea, and all <hi>England</hi> to imitate in all Ceremonies, both at Church and Tavern; and let the uſe of <hi>Barkin</hi> be for ever here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after accounted better than all the reſt (<hi>Sarum</hi> only excepted.)</p>
                        <p>Now let's drown all animoſities in a reconciling Bottle; and ſo in perfect charity, moſt Orthodox, and moſt ſeriouſly Devout <hi>Jonathan I</hi> bid you heartily farewel.</p>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <p>REceived from Mr. <hi>Sherman,</hi> Late Upper Churchwarden, This written Narrative with his order to put the ſame among the Pariſh Papers, but not to deliver it into Veſtry, until after Evening Sermon on <hi>Sunday</hi> 17th of <hi>April,</hi> 1681. becauſe the Lord Biſhop of <hi>London</hi> is not only to preach, but alſo to ſolemnize the publick confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of ſuch Children, or elder Perſons in this Pariſh as have the Certificate of the Reverend Dr. <hi>Hicks,</hi> which, among others, Mr. <hi>Sherman</hi>'s own Children are all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided with, in order to his Lordſhips Benediction, and therefore leſt any heats ſhould ariſe, Mr. <hi>Sherman</hi>'s order to me, is, not to deliver it till after all that Solemnity is over; and if there be no Veſtry then, to deliver it to Mr. <hi>Hunter</hi> and Mr. <hi>Chapman</hi> the preſent Churchwardens;</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Signed by</hi> G. Whately <hi>Regiſter to the Veſtry of the Pariſh of</hi> All Saints Barkin, London.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </postscript>
               <postscript>
                  <head>POTSCRIPT.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>To Mr. <hi>Saunders,</hi> ſince added.</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>SIR, A word more before we part, let the World be Judge and Jury to try theſe matters between you and I.</p>
                  <p>Whether a Carved Image be any Ornament to the Commandments? If not, then why did you in your firſt Apparition, <hi>Pag.</hi> 1. Print thus, it was ſet as an Ornament over the Ten Commandments? Why in the ſame Page do you Print as ſpoken by the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor that he conceived it was their duty to conſult the Veſtry, are not Churchwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens to learn their duty from the Law, rather then from the Veſtry or Parſon; may not the adviſe of the Parſon tend to incroach Pariſh Right, and if the Churchwarden ſuffer it to be enter'd in Veſtry Regiſter; may it not hereafter be pleaded the Parſons Right by Cuſtome as having ſuch a Precedent?</p>
                  <p>What if the Parſon tells us it is his right to chooſe one Churchwarden, nay what if he tells us he will chooſe both; or elſe perhaps be ſo civil as to take 30 for his Aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants, by the name of a <hi>Select Veſtry,</hi> where there are 200 inhabitants; and ſo exclude the other 170, from ſuch right of chooſing any Officers in that Pariſh, as the Law allows them; are we bound to loſe ſuch Right?</p>
                  <p>Why? do you in the ſame Page print as the Doctors opinion, that the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardens defence was <hi>neceſſary</hi> and <hi>eaſie?</hi> Is it <hi>neceſſary</hi> to defend <hi>Images,</hi> or are <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages</hi> at all <hi>neceſſary</hi> in Churches? alſo can it be <hi>eaſie</hi> to defend <hi>Images,</hi> when there is a Law to aboliſh all Images and Pictures (except ſuch as are upon Tombs and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numents?) What need had you (in the ſame Page) to alarm all Chapels and Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drals?
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:98858:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>will they or any Proteſtant but you Print any thing in defence of ſuch an Image ſet in ſuch a place, and call it an <hi>Ornament</hi> to the Ten Commandements?</p>
                  <p>Was it reaſonable for you to intimate <hi>Fol.</hi> 2. as if it were not known on what Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute the Indictment of this Image could be grounded though you may have a bad memory yet you can read if you look on your book, as you uſe to do; and there <hi>Page</hi> 1. You have quoted the Statute your ſelf in the Mergin, <hi>Anno</hi> 3 <hi>&amp;</hi> 4, <hi>Edw. VI. c.</hi> 10.</p>
                  <p>Is my Narrative or your two Printed Apparitions trueſt Relations of the matter; did my Burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this Image privately in a Veſtry Chimney, or your two printed Apparitions, ſpread the News and Noiſe furtheſt: which was the better deed, my burning or your printing? who minded their own buſineſs moſt, the Lecturer or the Churchwarden in ſo doing? is it not a great abuſe (at leaſt) if not a mighty prophanation of the name and order of <hi>Godfather</hi> which the Church hath ſo ſolemnly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned, for a <hi>Clergyman</hi> to call a Wooden Image Mr. <hi>Shermans</hi> Godſon. I have heard that Papiſts do Chriſten their Images, but I never heard that Images had <hi>Godfathers</hi> before Mr. <hi>Saunders</hi> printed it: but take notice that no Prieſt of S. <hi>Michael</hi> ſhall ever make me ſtand Godfather to a Wooden I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage.</p>
                  <p>Suppoſe the Act of <hi>Edward</hi> the <hi>VI.</hi> was made only for aboliſhing ſuch Maſs Books and ſuch Images as were then in being; will your Learning Convince a Jury, that it is lawful to print thoſe Maſs Books, and new make the ſame Images and bring them into Churches again, by ſaying, Theſe are not the ſame Books nor the ſame Images meant by that Act to be aboliſhed, becauſe you can prove that theſe were lately printed, or the Image made by Mr. <hi>Edwards?</hi> by this Logick you would make the fancy of Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> the Churchwarden for ſetting up Images to be of more force then the Law of <hi>Edward</hi> the King was for aboliſhing all Images: (except, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>)</p>
                  <p>Whether we ought not to petition the Lord Biſhop to Command you to keep ſuch evaſive Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gick in defence of Images to your ſelf, and not print as is in Page 1.</p>
                  <p>And would it not be better, if the Biſhop did Command you to keep at your Living at <hi>Sandon</hi> and not for Lucre of a Lecture is place at <hi>London</hi> (where is no want of good Miniſters) neglect your Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in teaching your people of <hi>Sandon</hi> their Duty and Ceremonies: and let the Liquor and Company of your Pariſhoners at <hi>Sandon,</hi> Content you better then what you and either at <hi>London</hi> or <hi>Chelmsford,</hi> and leave us of <hi>Barking</hi> to uſe our Ceremonies, as we did till the Plot broke out, and not make our Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh of <hi>Barking</hi> be thus talkt on for Images once in Forty years, by your thus nicking the time with your Bowings and Doppings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>You ſay in your ſecond Apparition, that I ſingly Pleaded guilty to the indictment, but one of our late <hi>London Intelligences,</hi> told you in print, that it ought to be Recorded for a Lie: becauſe it is a Lie againſt a Record, for Mr. <hi>Hunter</hi> was at the Seſſions, and did alſo Plead Guilty at the ſame time and place, and it is Recorded that Mr. <hi>Hunter</hi> pleaded Guilty.</p>
                  <p>Though he that Kills a man unawares hath mercy; yet wilful premeditated murther is death without benefit of Clergy: ſo if a Lecturer <hi>not having the fear of God before his Eyes,</hi> ſhould ſtudy and premeditate how to ſpread untruths and ſcandals furtheſt, by printing them; ought he to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed to plead benefit of his Clergy or to have any protection from an Action at <hi>Law;</hi> and if a Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cturer ſhall do all this <hi>Prava Mentis,</hi> (your own Apparition words) may I not Anſwer (alſo in your own Apparition words) <hi>that it is to paſs for a voluntary deſigned prevarication,</hi> and is it not a pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful low ſpirit (your own words) <hi>of a thing,</hi> who I was a going to call Lecturer, <hi>to think to gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie ſome one party of men</hi> (which are alſo your apparition words:) by ſcandalizing a Churchwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den in print: and by printing falſe ſtories of a poor Clark alſo with deſign to turn a Clark out of his place, who perhaps, If he were heard, might ſhew more cauſe to turn out the Lecturor: (Now in your own Apparition words again) you ought to Remember, <hi>he that ſells his Neighbours ſame</hi> (though a poor Clark, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) <hi>for a little unſavoury and popular breath, will in Concluſion gain nothing but infamy and diſgrace.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I hope, you will not blame me for ſpeaking in your own Language, nor for giving one Anſwer to two frightful Apparitions of an Angel; that never was ſeen in Apparition but by a Lecturer, nor hath ever ſcared any body elſe a month out of town, nor did any Miracle before its burning; ſave bringing a Lecturer to perform Ceremonies and bow at the place it ſtood, which the Lecturer never did before the Image was theſe: prethee, fancy that you ſtill ſee the Apparition of the ſame Angel there, and bow and dop as low as you pleaſe for now I am out of my Office, I ſit where I can hear and ſee well enough my ſelf, but pray take care the Women may hear.</p>
                  <p>I intend no Reflection on the Clergy or Church of <hi>England</hi> nor one Mr. <hi>Tho Whitebread,</hi> though I had occaſion to mention him; therefore whatever Reflection may ſeem to be on any body, I charge you and your printed Apparitions to be the occaſion: and pray you to apply all to your own ſelf, that nothing may ſeem to Reflect on our reverend and learned Doctor <hi>Hicks,</hi> nor on the Veſtry, nor on any of the worthy Gentlemen of our Pariſh; who I ſuppoſe will not take part with you or me in defence of this Image, but leave you to defend your Printing, and me my Burning, as well as we can O then we ſhall all practiſe what you uſe to preach <hi>viz. That everyone ſhould mind his own buſineſs.</hi>
                  </p>
               </postscript>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:98858:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
